how did you describe mine well
here's one way is
it's tough
faculty the body so are we talking
about mono that's that's what I was
looking back I was just thinking man I
don't know Superman of it okay nice to
be the Dhammapada bus yes we were
beginning yep it's all of the writings
are preceded by mind the Florence
excelled by mind made by mind mind by
amazing manner as in mono mono mono
become mono to say tell mother Maya to
its mono can intellect deal with
thoughts rationale I don't really I
don't really think of it well I was
thinking a bit more as I guess its
bodily in the sense like yeah idea then
I was this part of the sixth Emanuel Ax
to me I mean yes it bottling dealing
with thoughts as in not necessarily
understanding it yeah yeah that's it so
so you can't even you can't even
positively defined define mono like Oman
is this no because it would be a
thoughts exactly
so you can discern it is money in the
same sense you can say this is my eye
than I'm seeing yeah decision yeah for
monolith descend the basis of the I on a
kind of present sites so it's sort of so
he's the mind conceivable without a
thought no so when you think mind does
that thought that and that thought is
made possible because Milo's holding
yeah but what is mine orderly there so
that's another thought yeah that way so
I can you know that there is mine
[Music]
something making this possible
well he knows something without thinking
it here account so I'll key them used as
in a sentence something makes this
possible when I can't even conceive
something making this possible here
stuck inside of mind so ok those that we
know he can have thoughts
so I guess it's just later I just want
to say it's the necessary basis for sure
the little correct theoretical on ya
akhi no necessary basis I mean how can
you even conceive that even as a
theoretical designation I guess because
if you rec if you know that these
thoughts this anything I could imagine
it is impermanent it's basically on
ownable it's online on reachable because
it's fully dependent on something which
is mine okay I mean the first two thirds
of that sentence I couldn't believe it
but how can you say oh this is
unrighteous to describing a direct
experience these thoughts are
impermanent they're the turn each other to death
they're the turn each other to death
because of the mind but not of
experience this correspond to that
because of the mind just at that strip
part or just something that's beyond me
again how can you conceive yeah yeah if
it's beyond you it's inconceivable that
but then so if you can even conceive a
direction oh it means it's sweden's it's
within yeah so where's the problem there
what's the problem
and is it problem there well yeah I
guess this this idea of there being
something beyond the mind beyond the
mind that I have thought thought hasn't
mean like outside of thoughts outside of
yeah that's that's what
the notion of mind plans itself saying
this idea of something that is beyond
the thought so what was the other what's
what's the common thread between this
what we talked about in the other to
some college we're speaking about what's
the nature of ignorance plus Sankara
what does it result in do you mean with
the assumption of something outside
exactly so that's exactly what you've
been doing now when I ask you what is
the mind you start with a base of
thought but then provide an external
description of a necessary basis or else
which is how is that even conceivable
how can you conceive the outside of the
present enduring thought yeah and that's
why the mind is the particular the the
most fundamental appropriation and
assumption potential is assuming
external you can stop assuming
externally regard to bodies stop
assuming external even a regard to
speech but ceasing to assume external
reading after your own thought mm-hmm
serious that's slightly over order hmm
so keeping that in mind what is the mind
what is well
and I say anything differently without
without trying to designate something
which is outside of my thoughts so what
is a necessary basically then go to mind well well
Bhati
more specifically they were feeling and
perceptions you know that's a different
mind okay pizza okay except the
necessary those are necessary thoughts
thoughts you cannot exactly in the same sense you
you cannot exactly in the same sense you
cannot even conceive you there are eyes
unless their sites yes but more
specifically now within that specific
answer yeah
what aspect of thoughts Oh necessary
basis for mind yes some color like what
has black they want characteristic of
thoughts he's the necessary basis what
he's the necessary basis what
characteristic of the sights even
necessary basis for existence of the
eyes sort of thinking like them sort of
peripheral oh it's not supposed to okay
yeah but once that I'm more specifically
just take a thought yeah peripheral
thought whichever what internal
characteristic of a third characteristic
property can you finish sense what
constant what into not electricity what
it's a no property of the enduring
thought is the necessary basis for mine
yes based on which you can discern the -
indirectly because you can't
intentionally look at the mind no you
can't intentionally think your way
through to the man yes but you can
discern the property of the enduring
thought to see that the mind can see
outside of it
so what is that property and that it's
related to what thoughts no that's an
external property between the two
sources is no internal property eight
and is a little of an enduring for what that it's
that has manifested on its own exactly
that's it
the two-degree is this gym design with
sights sounds smells tastes touches to
that degree they're independent to
declare their independence they are
unknowable and you realize that degrees
the degree that comes first now you can
access as your ownership you can think
this you can talk about that on top of
the degree of the resistance is it there
is absolutely not a trace of the
resistance manifested well you get a
manifest maybe nothing this era okay
yeah and to that degree that's where the
mind is so it's not on the level of you
thinking all over you using the
intellect it's on the level of learning
the degree of the dependence of those
thoughts they can't proceed your
intentionality I don't quite see how
that that clarifies the mind
well clarifies the mind in a sense that
can resistance of a thought be outside
of a thought can get it resistance of a
thought beyond sight thoughtful no can
you even define it even abstractly no it
is systems of what without saying what
so it's inconceivable to miss conceived
it outside of the thought and that's
basically what in mind it
so the manifestation of a thought in its
impermanence to that extent that we the
mind is
but it seems to me like as if you're
still looking for a positive definition
of what a mind is yeah no I'm just still
not planning on doing it yeah yeah so so
well can you see the resistance can you
see the resistance of an enduring
thought you see the resistance of an
enduring thought yeah that's it's has
arisen on its own okay well that's what
the mind is why do you think it's it's
it's relevant why do you think the mind
is the forerunner of all things because
if you don't see them as impermanent he
determines a whole direction of us
impermanence ownership design plus
perversion everything else if a 10 level
you don't ignore the reason independence
resistance an own ability or faith Lord
the mind doesn't go down those paths
selves sir yes sir then the necessary
basis can be revealed indirectly exactly
yeah and he says no this is a neutral basis
and he says no this is a neutral basis
like it sounded our figures were
unaffected so you may probably well not
the way I put this but by sort of not
ignoring the the fact that these
thoughts have just been
thriving pop you know that just that
that kind of reveals the fact that there
is a necessary basis for those which
isn't me that's true it is true our mind
isn't it and in order to avoid the
danger of falling into abstract because
there's a Buddha said himself
the mind is hard to see discern under
the ownership off because it's fleeting
it's quicker to think of it practically
thank your letters basically mindful of
the body right here right now presently
living easier body's still here alive
yes while their body is here alive
either also you can use to it but kind
of independent of it says are not
directly linearly related to it are
there also moods enduring feelings is
there feeling present yeah that's like
that's all I guess that's kind of all
anyway I can know that there is a body
there sure depends yeah differently so
so you have a fear of an enduring body
you have another care of an enduring
feeling yeah you have another theater
which is
what's your over removed and based on
the president during feelings neutral
neutrals so would you describe that
neutral mood as independent of your
feeling hang on you're different chicken
maybe you're feeling yeah like how are
you feeling will feel neutrally yeah
what you mood now positive between
negative - I fear not for things over
not having elated depressed no so even
even if you leave you can't say it
feeling is even you can say feeling is
pleasant unpleasant neutral but you can
say that your mood based in feeling is
even yeah but what does that also
involved the description of evenness it
involves how you feel
yes and it involves how you Percy yeah
bottom think so what is that thing that
that is inseparable from how you feel
and how you perceive chitta exactly so
that's another tear and then there is a
fourth tier of what you're actually
presently enduring thoughts but what
Damas are they're enduring what
phenomena have arisen on the most sort
of pinpoint level
natural phenomena that my general way
also generally depends in the content
yeah the particular in the nature in
general yeah but say you have a thought
of impermanence yeah again should a
mindful of it it's particular thought if
you're mindful of it it reveals the
general nature of all phenomena so what
are these four tears and I just
described savasana exactly and that's
why they're four foundations of
mindfulness and that's why any of them
can serve to develop mindfulness to the
extent necessary for the final knowledge
isin develop mindfulness to descendants
City for the file uprooting the desire
last in aversion
and that's how you practically develop
the mind or understand man because take
the present enduring feeling you say
it's neutral hmm
isn't that also thought yeah course take
President Lee enduring body well what's
your body posture coroner sets it down
what's your health status currently
healthy feel from physical discomfort
yeah no discomfort again our our indoors
all this thing that you just designate
describe also so right so it's 40 years
they do all contain each other basically
yeah because take the fear of thought
present enduring body so you have a
thought of seated posture here would you
be able to have that thought unless
there is actual physical body would you
there is also awareness of basically the
whole experience in regard to their body
which is already highly feeling much of
this year another
isn't that thought also perceived yeah
isn't the perception also felt felt yeah
so they're artists so it's four aspects
of experiences or wherever you look
they're all for that if you look at them
rightly exactly you look at one the
other three are in it that's why I knew
thank you sir for a mindful aesthetics
and necessary for the final knowledge
and that's one of them can serve for you
to a food assumption of external to what
you're experiencing yes because they can
you assume external of your present
enduring feeling no is that even
conceivable you have it out though right
I mean there is there is something
but isn't that is within what you feel
exactly it's just in cooked like so I
have the present enduring feeling
neutral feeling yesterday I felt a bit
different but I'm still on the basis of
the basis it to that exact so it's it's
inconceivable yeah not dwelling on it
sufficiently enough there is
inconceivable you keep consuming it completely true
you keep consuming it completely true
yeah so if you want to understand mono
and Damas
develop mindfulness of the body properly
don't understand masters of the body
properly yeah
develop mindfulness abdominals in mother
because you'll be understanding the
resisting aspect then you'll be
understanding the designation as Pavelec
basically because can you know that
there is as I said that there is a
seated body here and now unless there is
also thought of it and see even that
question unless there is also thought
implies there's something else with the
thought what is that something else
unless that's another thought yeah is
then thought outside of your thought how
is it possible impossible
all there is is thoughts one reduces
thoughts that resist yeah and the
designate yeah yeah
the designation part is the word
intentions are where you intended follow
that's with an if all exists is thought
people all it's all in my head right
yeah sure it's all in your head did also
resist you yeah means that you can on
yeah so yes I thought of the body is
what the body is yeah because if they
were nobody resisting it that is also
being thought while it's resisting isn't
so let's say so you might say and so I'm
thinking of the body and so that's a
thought but then that then you might
think well that's a thought of the body
which is something not that's not a
thought but that's how could I you know
I don't see you as your means yeah yeah
so I don't usually get outside of this
that's you not practicing satavahanas
one within the other but practicing in
one two three four which means you don't
see any of them yeah if you think their
linear arrangement of methods means you
you don't understand what mindfulness is
so you have a thought of the body
well you might that thought of the body
might start with it more of a resisting
aspect of the thought of the body which
is this body enduring here
yeah and that induced within that
present enduring basis of the body
that's a thought yes there is also
present unit feeling yeah there are
perceptions yeah their intentions these
are the things that now you see
correctly within the container of the
present enduring body if you start
looking at the content of the present
enduring body you say off so this is the
thought and you have to be careful now
because that designation if you miss
conceive it it can then assume external
to itself as a new say oh this body is a
thought or even more blatantly this body
is just a thought
well implies then this is just a thought
and then there is that which is a real
body yeah house for outside before how
can you even finish the sentence there
is that which is the real body unless
that's already a thought so what you're
saying there is a thought and there is a
real thought and there is a thought and
there is a thought that's how my but the
thing is that deeply-rooted
it is that's why did the entire world as
the Buddha said falls into a proven or
method or discipline of the matter as in
affirmation or denial as in was
eternalists or annihilation it's and
yeah it's all rooted in it puts even the
thought shares the same principle the
same pattern of ignorance okay so can
you say rather than so having the idea
of this this thoughts of the body which
then leads wants a think of a body that
that is a thought off which is outside
of thorns is it so yes so now you got to
say every new fool in the body there
leads one to think off yeah another
thought that we sever that yet another
thought exactly so so basically instead
of thinking in that linear way I guess
it's rather you can only understand what
matter is or what the body is through
that thoughts yeah yes but even if that
won't be let's see if you if you come if
you still carry on like an implicit
assumption it I can understand real man
yeah the thought that is inconceivable what
the thought that is inconceivable what
is the aspect of real how do you know
that unless you're thinking it yeah yet
it's assumed as an external reality they
precede your thought oh this is the real
the whole idea is not beyond and you
know that the the the reality behind the
conventions yeah how can you speak of it
unless it's another convention and
that's when people don't know how to
escape this don't don't know how to deal
with the problem of assumption so then
they blame the designation they say the
conventions designations words names now
that's the problem
yeah so you stop doing it you get to the
real reality that you just name it
exactly yeah and then you realize the
naming is not a matter of choice either
because whenever there is a degree of
resistance there you go you just name it
and a degree of resistance
yeah and that's not to new that's what I
said the target understands the extent
of designations Ignatian just means
something to recognize it doesn't
necessarily mean you've given if you do
it yeah sure labeling naming come out of
the exact but it's far down the road but
then just the registration that's
something that people don't have to deal
with the problem so then they try to
identify it with labeling and naming of
which is easily dismissable yeah just
refrain from naming and then a reality
you can't refrain from thoughts that's
ordered a designation in itself that
resists you sorry you can't refrain from
you can refrain from engaging upon so in
a certain manner yeah we can't refrain
from having thoughts ahead and those
thoughts are already designated to that
extent that they resist you and they do
resist you because again they appear to
you yeah for you yeah
so mindfulness of the body is then
mindful of your thoughts yeah
mindfulness of the thought properly as I
said to be discerning the extent the
thought resists you ordered implies
fundamental resistance which is
resistance of the senses and the body so
mindfulness of the thoughts properly
means mindfulness of the body properly
and everything in between in between
being feelings in yeah because otherwise
inconceivable without feeling some needs
attention it's just inseparable from so you can
it's just inseparable from so you can
take him pick the aspect you want to do
but you'll be developing all them if you
are doing in writing yeah but you don't
need to kind of look at the other one no
you just yeah it's yes if you're
comparing them we are you have none
and also another thing to mention is
they tell you say okay so this is I have
a thoughts of this body and you can't
help but imply that there is death
outside of this thought from which this
body has come so to speak and again
that's no matter of choice so you can't
stop doing that you can't remove that
implication by choice but you will
approach the implication by including it
yeah it's something else because exactly
to the extended assumes extent external
to that extent exclude itself yeah oh
this potentially this thought that's
within the domain of thoughts their true
loosely somehow implies that it's
outside of this domain authority as and
I can conceive anything outside of my
senses yeah and like that's again it's
it's in the same it's the same nature
same principle what we described when
what you think you're accessing the the
objects of your senses wholly can
exercise your body yeah yeah all you can
access is your senses being affected by
different things see different things
means outside of my senses no yeah
that's the implication but once you
fully understand it so you're not to do
no I must stop something in this
implication that's impossible
you can't stop thinking it but I should
include it within the necessary
contended with the present enduring body
not excluded as something outside yeah
that's how the Assumption aspect of it
fades yeah but thoughts in itself was never a
yeah but thoughts in itself was never a
problem even a wrong thought is not a
problem in itself yeah the problem is
the the significance that the diggity
really carries see anything there is a
real reality behind my reality or the
real boil behind my senses or the
scientific public world that I can that
we all access through our senses and
it's all very measurable by us
individually and collectively
how can you discern any of that any
scope of that domain unless you're
thinking it exactly which is fine to
think it but it's not find it when you
think it you think that your thought is
second to it yeah yeah the only way to
know it is to think it it's basically
that's the order list
always yeah that's the whole point from
that perverted orderly the most
fundamental level of down mine mono mono
is the forerunner of all things river
the order mono is the forerunner of all
perverted things perversion of lots
diversion and distraction you approve
it's like you know polluted stream on
top of the mountain yeah doesn't matter
how far down you go it's gonna carry the
same pollution doesn't matter how much
how hard you tried to purify the water
at the lower points your work is endless
because you're not approaching it at a
source but then you go and find the
source and clear the pollution in the
very source then you don't have to worry
about doesn't matter even if it turns
into whole ocean later on does matter
did you know it cannot be polluted
because you're cleaning up the source
and the source if the mind and the
thoughts what the mind is definable by
the resistance of the thoughts present
in urine thought president enduring
thought of the body president hearing
thought of the feeling resonating
thought of the mind the mood present in
universe of impermanence present
enduring thought of suffering even
presently enduring thought so if you
can't own any of this I can own any of
this and the thought that I can't any I
can own any of this are unknowable if I
understand them is unknowable
no idea wanna ship came entertaining in
regard to anything inferior to them
anything within there
and so will and all them perceptions
sights sounds smells disco or
that's all secondary sure
that's oh it said the five senses
meeting them exactly but it's not like
they I think many people today tend to
think that that that that's the kind of
building blocks and then they come and
they meet in the module I construct it
together and then reality constructed by
the mind
how can you conceive that I think that's
pre exact reality exactly how can even
theorize about pre reality unless you're
theorizing it in the real time here now
which is your reality yet here you are
using the reeds of this reality which is
the means of resisting thoughts that
designate to describe that which
precedes this resistance and designation
and somehow assume the validity of that
world it's actually inaccessible to you
so you assuming the axis that's how
these things exist that's what will set
the four Great elements find the footing
your experience could you conceive them
you give them the being through your
misconceiving literally that's what they
are otherwise they cannot appear they
can only resist and that's already
designated and that's already the level
of the mind
so present enduring feeling you can
approach as a present enduring feeling
I'm feeling like this while I'm doing
this well I'm feeling like this while
I'm talking feeling like this one
breathing a feeling of it I'm still
feeling the same while we are sitting in
discussing this or you can approach a
present during feeling you're also
present in every thought yeah because it
is the thought isn't it exactly but
obviously can you have that thought if
there isn't present in you natira can
you know the president you are feeling
if there isn't if it isn't a thought if
it isn't an image if indonesian Adama
impossible
that there's a tendency to thing that is
feeling like it's a saint
yeah that's women if you're comparing
the approaches you're not doing either
it's a serve and the way to avoid that
is to include the feeling within so sure
you include your need to compare yeah
just as enduring feeling well within any
present enduring tiered mmm within any
present enduring anger so you can think
about the thoughts on the basis of being
mindful of the president during body
yeah you can think about feeling on the
basis of present in your thoughts
whichever way you do to your mindfulness
that's fine but it will have to be
routine one of these four things is
nothing outside of these tears that you
can think or experience that's not
within one of them which applies all the
other ones